let set5=
[
    {
        question:`1. Match the List-I with List-II and select the correct answer
        using the code given below :
        List-I (soil layers) List II (their specifications)
        A. Top soil or A-horizon        1.This layer is soft, porous and can retain more water.
        B. Middle layer or B-horizon    2.It is made up of small lumps of rocks with cracks & crevices.
        C. Third layer or C-horizon     3.Lesser amount of humus but more of minerals.
        D. Bedrock                      4. It is hard and difficult to dig it with a spade.
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 2 3 4',
            'B. 1 3 2 4',
            'C. 3 4 1 2',
            'D. 2 1 4 3',
            
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: A vertical section through different layers of the soil
        is called the soil profile. Each layer differs in feel (texture), colour,
        depth and chemical composition. These layers are referred to as
        horizons.
        The uppermost horizon is generally dark in colour as it is rich in
        humus and minerals. The humus makes the soil fertile and provides
        nutrients to growing plants. This layer is generally soft, porous and
        can retain more water. It is called the topsoil or the A-horizon. This
        provides shelter for many living organisms such as worms, rodents,
        moles and beetles. The roots of small plants are embedded entirely
        in the topsoil.
        The next layer has a lesser amount of humus but more of minerals.
        This layer is generally harder and more compact and is called the Bhorizon or the middle layer.
        The third layer is the C-horizon, which is made up of small lumps of
        rocks with cracks and crevices. Below this layer is the bedrock,
        which is hard and difficult to dig with a spade.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`2. Consider the following assertions:
        1. The best topsoil for growing plants is loamy.
        2. Loamy soil is a mixture of sand,clay and slit.
        3. The size of the silt particles is between those of sand and clay.
        4. Sandy soil is suitable for growing wheat, gram and paddy.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 1, 2 and 3 only',
'C. 3 and 4 only',
'D. 1, 2, 3 and 4',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: The best topsoil for growing plants is loam. Loamy soil
        is a mixture of sand, clay and another type of soil particle known as
        silt. Silt occurs as a deposit in river beds. The size of the silt
        particles is between those of sand and clay.
        The loamy soil also has humus in it. It has the right water holding
        capacity for the growth of plants.
        Clayey soil and loamy soil are suitable for growing wheat, gram and
        paddy, as they have good amount of humus in them; while cotton is
        grown in sandy soil and loamy soil, which facilitate quick draining of
        water.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`3. During heavy exercise, we get cramps in the legs due to the accumulation of?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Carbon dioxide',
'B. Lactic acid',
'C. Water',
'D. Alcohol',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: During heavy exercise, fast running , cycling, walking
        for many hours or heavy weight lifting, the demand for energy is
        high. But the supply of oxygen to produce the energy is limited. Then
        anaerobic respiration takes places in the muscle cells to fulfil the
        demand of energy. The partial breakdown of glucose produces lactic
        acid. The accumulation of lactic acid causes muscle cramps. We can
        get relief from cramps after a hot water bath or a massage. Hot
        water bath or massage improves circulation of blood. As a result, the
        supply of oxygen to the muscle cells increases. The increase in the
        supply of oxygen results in the complete breakdown of lactic acid
        into carbon dioxide and water.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`4. What is the percentage of oxygen in inhaled and exhaled air, respectively?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. 21% and 16.4%',
'B. 4% and 21%',
'C. 48% and 24%',
'D. 24% and 14%',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: Breathing means taking in air rich in oxygen and giving
        out air rich in carbon dioxide with the help of respiratory organs.
        The taking in of air rich in oxygen into the body is called inhalation
        and giving out of air rich in carbon dioxide is known as exhalation.
        Inhaled air contains 21% oxygen and 0.04% carbon dioxide, while the
        exhaled air contains 16.4% oxygen and 4.4% carbon dioxide.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`5. In the context of respiration in various animals, consider the following assertions —
        1. The process of breakdown of food in the cell with the release of energy is called cellular respiration.
        2. In the cell, the food (glucose) is broken down into carbon dioxide and water using oxygen.
        3. Food can also be broken down, without using oxygen. This is called aerobic respiration.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. 3 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation: when breakdown of glucose occurs with the use of
        oxygen, it is called aerobic respiration; whereas food can also be
        broken down, without using oxygen. This is called anaerobic
        respiration.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`6. Which of the following terms, is/are transported in the body, through blood? :
        1. Digested food
        2. Oxygen
        3. Waste material
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 1 and 2 only',
'C. 2 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation: Blood is the fluid which flows in blood vessels. It
        transports substances like digested food from the small intestine to
        the other parts of the body. It carries oxygen from the lungs to the
        cells of the body. It also transports waste for removal from the
        body.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`7. What is the function of white blood cells or granules?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Carry oxygen',
'B. Carry carbon-dioxide',
'C. Fight against germs',
'D. Clot blood',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C
        Explanation: Blood is composed of a fluid, called plasma in which
        different types of cells are suspended.
        These cells are of 3 types —
        1. Red blood cells (RBC)
        2. White blood cells (WBC)
        3. Platelets
        Red blood cells transport oxygen to all the parts of the body and
        ultimately to all the cells.White blood cells fight against germs that
        may enter our body, while the clot is formed because of the
        presence of another type of cells in the blood, called platelets.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`8. Consider the following:
        1. Blood
        2. Blood vessels
        3. Heart
        4. Renal (kidney)
        Which of the above organs is/are not the part of the human
        circulatory system?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 3 only',
'B. 2 and 3 only',
'C. 3 and 4 only',
'D. 4 only',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation:
        1. Blood circulation was discovered by an English physician, William
        Harvey.
        2. Blood, blood vessels and heart are all part of the human
        circulatory system.
        3. Blood transports substances like digested food from the small
        intestine to the other parts of the body. It carries oxygen from the
        lungs to the cells of the body.
        4. There are two types of blood vessels present in the body -
        arteries and veins. Arteries carry oxygen-rich blood from the heart
        to all parts of the body. Since the blood flow is rapid and at a high
        pressure, the arteries have thick elastic walls.
        5. Veins are the vessels which carry carbon dioxide-rich blood from
        all parts of the body back to the heart. The veins have thin walls.
        There are valves present in veins which allow blood to flow only
        towards the heart.
        6. The heart is an organ which beats continuously to act as a pump
        for the transport of blood, which carries other substances with it.
        7. The renal is part of the Excretory system in humans and not the
        circulatory system.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`9. Consider the following:
        1. Fish
        2. Hydra
        3. Sponge
        In which of the above organisms, no circulatory system is found?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 1 and 2 only',
'C. 2 and 3 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C
        Explanation: There is no circulatory system in animals like Hydra
        and sponges. The water in which they live, enters their bodies and
        supplies them with food and oxygen.When water comes out, it also
        brings carbon dioxide and waste materials along with it.Therefore,
        they do not need any blood-like fluid for circulation.Normally the
        circulatory system is found in fishes.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`10. Match List I to List II and select the correct answer with the code given below:
        List-I (Parts of Plants) List-II (Their Work)
        A. Stomata      1.Transport of food
        B. Xylem        2.Transport of water
        C. Phloem       3.Transpiration
        D. Root hair    4.Water absorption
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 4 2 3 1',
'B. 4 1 2 3',
'C. 3 2 1 4',
'D. 3 4 1 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C`
    }
]